<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The art of iugling or legerdemaine Wherein is deciphered, all the conueyances of legerdemaine and iugling, how they are effected, and wherein they chiefly consist. Cautions to beware of cheating at cardes and dice. The detection of the beggerly art of alcumistry. And, the foppery of foolish cousoning charmes. All tending to mirth and recreation, especially for those that desire to haue the insight and priuate practise thereof. By S.R.</title>
            <author>Rid, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10750</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842806</idno>
  <idno type="VID">7497</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240870297</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 21028</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S107103</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99842806e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10750)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 683:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The art of iugling or legerdemaine Wherein is deciphered, all the conueyances of legerdemaine and iugling, how they are effected, and wherein they chiefly consist. Cautions to beware of cheating at cardes and dice. The detection of the beggerly art of alcumistry. And, the foppery of foolish cousoning charmes. All tending to mirth and recreation, especially for those that desire to haue the insight and priuate practise thereof. By S.R.</title>
                  <author>Rid, Samuel.</author>
                  <author>Greene, Robert, 1558?-1592, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.    </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Eld,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>S.R. = Samuel Rid.</note>
                  <note>Often wrongly ascribed to Robert Greene--Folger Shakespeare Library catalog.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  B-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Juggling --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Magic tricks --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Swindlers and swindling --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7497:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7497:1"/>
            <p>THE ART OF IVGLING OR Legerdemaine. WHEREIN IS DECIPHERED, all the conueyances of Legerdemaine and Iugling, how they are effected, and wherein they chiefly consist. Cautions to beware of cheating at Cardes and Dice. The detection of the beggerly Art of Alcumistry. And, The foppery of foolish cousoning Charmes. All tending to mirth and recreation, especially for those that desire to haue the insight and priuate practise thereof. By S. R.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quod noua testa capit, Inueterata sapit.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by GEORGE ELD. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7497:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7497:2"/>
            <head>TO THE INGENIOVS GEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and my louing father, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. WILLIAM BVBB.</head>
            <l>THis short conceipt, that I haue writ of late,</l>
            <l>To you kinde father <hi>BVBB</hi> I dedicate,</l>
            <l>Not that I meane hereby (good Sir) to teach,</l>
            <l>For I confesse your skils beyond my reach:</l>
            <l>But since before with me much time you spent,</l>
            <l>Good reason then, first fruits <hi>I</hi> should present:</l>
            <l>That thankefull * Bird<note place="margin">The natu<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of this Bird<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that build<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> her nest vn<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the couer<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> houses (as t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Swallow do<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> with vs) leau<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> euer behin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> her for th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> owner of th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> house, o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> young one,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> token of h<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thankfulness<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and as I m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> say, for paw<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of her rent.</note> that leaues one young behinde,</l>
            <l>Ensamples me, to beare a thankefull minde:</l>
            <l>Vngratefull he, that thankes can not repay</l>
            <l>To him, that hath deseru'd it euery way:</l>
            <l>Accept (kinde Sir) my loue, that being doone,</l>
            <l>I aske no more, desire no other Boone.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing sonne in all loue, SA. RID.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <head>TO HIS LOVING FRIEND AND adopted Sonne M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Sa. Rid.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most worthy sonne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur labour and obseruance herein, with the gift of your first fruits, is both worthy commendations and acceptance: and to cherish you further in this your disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, I will giue an addition to your second treatise. So I leaue you to God: and belieue you, not a more louing friend then,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WILLIAM BVBB.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7497:3"/>
            <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE goeth a pretty Fable of the Moone: On a time she earnestly besought her mother to prouide her a garment, comely and fit for her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: how can that be sweet daughter (quoth the mother) sith that your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy nether keeps it self at any one stay, nor at one certaine estate, but chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth euery day in the month, nay euery houre? The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation hereof needs no interpretation: Fantasie and foolery who can please? and desire who can humour? no Camelion changeth his colour as affection, nor any thing so variable as <hi>Populus, Chorus, Fluuius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would with all my heart, euery Author that had done no better then I haue, had done no worse: and it were to be wished that some capricious Coxecombes, with their des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate wits, were not so forward to disbowell the entrails of their own ouerweening, singular, infectious, and pestiferous thoughts, as I know some.</p>
            <p>But I cannot stand all day nosing of Candlesticks: meane time beare with a plaine man: whatsoeuer I haue now done, I hope no exception can be taken, it is for your mirth and recreation (and I pray you so take it:) let such as will needs barke at the Moone, yell till their hearts ake: Gentle and Gentlemens spirits, will take all kindely that is kindely presented.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in loue, <hi>S. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7497:3"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Art of Iugling or Legerdemaine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eretofore we haue runne ouer the two pestiferous carbuncles in the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the Egiptians and common Canters: the poore Canters we haue canuased meetly well, it now remaines to proceed where I left, and to goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with that before I promised: St. <hi>Quintane</hi> be my good spéed, I know I haue run through the hands of many, censured of diuers, &amp; girded at not of a few: But humanity is euer willinger to loue then hate: curtesie much forwarder to commend then dispraise: clemency in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely proner to absolue then condemne. Is it not possible to find sauery hearbs among nettles, roses among prickles, berries among bushes, marrow among bones, graine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong stubble, &amp; a little corne among a great deale of chaffe? In the rankest &amp; strongest poysons, pure and swéet balmes may be distilled, and some matter or other worthy to be remembred may be embraced, whosoeuer is the Author. There is nothing so exceeding foolish but hath beene defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by some wise man, nor any thing so passing wise, but hath beene confuted by some foole: Tut St. <hi>Barnard</hi> saw not all thinges, and the best cart may eftsoones ouerthrow: That curld pate <hi>Rufus</hi> that goes about with <hi>Zoylus</hi> to carpe and find fault, must bring the Standard of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with him, and make wisedome the moderator of his wit, otherwise they may be like to purchase to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues
<pb facs="tcp:7497:4"/> the worshipfull names of <hi>Dunces</hi> and <hi>Dottipoles.</hi> So much by the way.</p>
            <p>These kind of people about an hundred yeares a goe, about the twentith yeare of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, began to gather an head, at the first héere about the Southerne parts, and this (as I am informed) and as I can gather, was their beginning.</p>
            <p>Certaine Egiptians, banished their Contry (belike not for their good conditions) ariued heere in England, who being excellent in quaint trickes and deuises, not knowne héere at that time among vs, were estéemed and had in great admiration, for what with strangenes of their atire and garments, together with their sleightes and leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demaines, they were spoke of farre and néere, insomuch that many of our English loyterers ioyned with them, and in time learned their craft and cosening. The speach which they vsed was the right Egiptian language, with whom our Englishmen conuersing, at last learned their language. These people continuing about the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey in this fashion, practising their cosoning art of fast and loose and legerdemaine, purchased to themselues great credit among the country people, and got much by Palmistry and telling of fortunes; insomuch they pittiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cosened the poore country Girles, both of money, sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer spoones, and the best of their apparrel, or any good thing they could make, onely to heare their fortunes.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Giles Hather</hi> (for so was his name) together with his whore <hi>Kit Calot,</hi> in short space had following them a pretty traine, hee tearming himselfe the King of the Egiptians, and she the Quéene, riding about the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try at their pleasures vncontrouled: at last about forty yeares after, when their knauery began to be espied, and th t their cosonages were aparant to the world (for they had continued néere thirty yeares after this manner, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; polling, &amp; cosening the cuntry) it pleased the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb facs="tcp:7497:4"/> to looke more narrowly into their liues, and in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament made in the first and second yeares of <hi>Phillip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> there was a strict Statute made, that whosoeuer should transport any Egiptians into this Realme, should forfeit forty poundes: Moreouer it was then enacted, that such fellowes as tooke vpon them the name of Egiptians aboue the age of fourteene, or that shal come ouer and be transported into England, or any other persons, and shal be séene in the company of Vagabonds calling themselues Egiptians, or counterfeiting, transforming, or disguising themselues by their apparrel, speach, or other behauiours like vnto Egiptians, and so shall continue, either at one, or seuerall times, by the space of a month, they should be adiudged fellons, not allowed their book or clergy. These Acts and Statutes now put forth, and come to their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, they deuide their bands and companies, into diuers parts of the realme: for you must immagine &amp; know that they had aboue two hundred roagues and Vagabonds in a regiment: and although they went not altogether, yet would they not bee aboue two or thrée miles one from the other, and now they dare no more bee known by the name of Egiptians, nor take any other name vpon them then poore people. But what a number were execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted presently vpon this statute you would wonder: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all would not preuaile: but stil they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, as before vp and downe, and méeting once in a yeare at a place appointed: sometimes at the Deuils arse in peak in Darbishire, &amp; otherwhiles at Ketbrooke by Black-heath, or elsewhere, as they agréed stil at their meeting. Then it pleased Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to reuine the Statute before mentioned, in the twentith yeare of her happy raigne, endeauoring by all meanes possible to root out this pestiferous people, but nothing could be done you see vntil this day they wander vp and downe in the name of Egiptians coulouring their faces and fashioning their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire,
<pb facs="tcp:7497:5"/> and garment like vnto them, yet if you aske what they are, they dare no otherwise then say, they are Englishmen, and of such a shire, and so are forced to say contrary to that they pretend.</p>
            <p>But to come a little neerer our purpose, these fellowes seeing that no profit comes by wandring, but hazard of their liues, do dayly decrease, and break off their wonted society, &amp; betake themselues many of them, some to be Ped<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers, some Tinkers, some Iuglers, &amp; some to one kind of life or other, insomuch that Iugling is now become common, I meane the professors who make an occupation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of the same: which I must needs say that some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue commendation for the nimblenes and agility of their hands, &amp; might be thought to performe as excellent things by their Legerdemaine, as any of your wizards witches or magitians whatsoeuer. For these kind of people do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that in action, which the other do make shew of: and no doubt many when they heare of any rare exploit perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med which cannot enter into their capacity, and is beyond their reach, straight they attribute it to be done by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, and that they work by some familiar spirit, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed it is nothing els but méere illusion, cosoning, or Leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demaine. For you haue many now a daies, and also héerto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many writers haue béen abused, aswell by vntrue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, as by illusion and practises of confederacy, &amp; leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demaine, &amp;c. Somtimes imputing to words that which resteth in nature, and somtimes to the nature of the thing that which proceedeth of fraud and deception of sight. But when these experiments grow to superstition and impiety they are eether to be forsaken as vayne: or denyed as false: howbeit if these thinges be done for recreation and mirth, &amp; not to the hurt of our neighbour, nor to the prophaning &amp; abusing of Gods holy name: then sure they are neither impious nor altogether vnlawfull, though heere in or heeereby a naturall thing be made to seeme supernaturall.
<pb facs="tcp:7497:5"/> And Gentlemen, if you will giue me patience, I wil lay open vnto you the right art of Iugling &amp; Legerdemain, in what poynt it doth chiefly consist: principally being sorry that it thus falls out, to lay open the secrets of this mistery to the hinderance of such poore men as liue thereby, whose doings heerein are not onely tollerable, but greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, so they abuse not the name of God, nor make the people to attribute vnto them his power, but alwayes acknowledge wherein the Art consisteth.</p>
            <p>The true Art therefore of Iuglers, consisteth in Leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demaine: that is, the nimble conueiance and right dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the hand, the which is performed diuers wayes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially three: The first and principall consisteth in hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and conueying of balls: The second in alteration of money: The third in the shuffling of Cardes: and hee that is expert in these, may shew many feates, and much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. There are diuers and rare experiments to be showne by confederacy, either priuate or publicke, al which in place conuenient shall be spoken of. And forasmuch as I professe rather to discouer then teach these misteries, it shal suffice to signifie vnto you, that the endeauour and drift of Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, is onely to abuse mens eyes and iudgements: now then my meaning is in wordes as plaine as I can to rip vp some proper tricks of that Art, whereof some are pleasant and delectable, othersome dreadfull &amp; desperate, and all but méere delusions, and counterfeit actions, as you shall soone see by due obseruation of euery knacke by me héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after deciphered: And first in order I wil begin with the plaies and deuises of the ball, which are many: I wil touch only but a few, and as in this, so in all the rest I will run ouer slightly yet as plaine as I can.</p>
            <div type="advice_to_jugglers">
               <pb facs="tcp:7497:6"/>
               <head>Notes and obseruations to be marked of such as desire to practise Legerdemaine.</head>
               <p>REmember that a Iugler must set a good face vppon that matter he goeth about, for a good grace and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is very requisite to make the art more authenticall. Your feates &amp; tricks then must be nimbly cleanly &amp; swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, and conueyed so as the eyes of the beholders may not discerne or perceaue the tricke, for if you be a bungler, you both shame your selfe, and make the Art you go about to bee perceiued and knowne, and soe bring it into dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit.</p>
               <p>Wherefore vse and excercise makes a man ready. <hi>Vsus promptos facit,</hi> and by that meanes your feats being cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly handled, you shall deceaue both the eye, the hand, and the eare: for often times it wil fall out in this art, and deuises <hi>Deceptio visus, Deceptio tactus, et Deceptio audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note also that you must haue none of your Trinkets wanting, least you be put to a nonplus: besides it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you to be mindful whereabout you go in euery trick, least you mistake and so discredit the art.</p>
               <p>You must also haue your words of art, certaine strange wordes, that it may not only breed the more admiration to the people, but lead away the eye from espying ner of your conueyance, while you may induce the mind the mind, to conceiue, and suppose that you deale with Spirits: and such kind of sentences, and od speeches, are vsed in diuers manners fitting and correspondent to the action and feat that you go about. As Hey <hi>Fortuna, furia, nunquam, Credo,</hi> passe passe, when come you Sirrah? or this way hey Iack come a loft for thy maisters aduantage passe and be gone, or otherwise: as <hi>Alif, Casil: zaze, Hit, metmeltat, Saturnus, Iupiter, Mars, Sol, Venus, Mercury,
<pb facs="tcp:7497:6"/> Luna?</hi> or thus <hi>Drocti, Micocti, et Senarocti, Velu barocti, Asmarocti, Ronnsee, Farounsee, hey passe passe:</hi> many such obseruations to this art are necessary, without which all the rest, are little to the purpose.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>Feates of Legerdemaine vsed with the Balls with one or more.</head>
               <p>COncerning the Ball, the plaies and deuises thereof are infinite: insomuch as if you can vse them wel, you may shew an hundred feates, but whether you seeme to throw the Ball into the aire, or into your mouth, or into your left hand, or as you list, it must be kept stil in your right hand: if you practise first with the leaden bullet you shal the sooner, &amp; better do it with balls of Corke: the first place at your first learning where you are to bestow a great bal is in the palme of your hand, with your ring fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but a smal ball is to be placed with your thumbe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your ring finger and middle finger: then are you to practise to doe it betwixt your other fingers, then betwixt the forefinger and the thumbe, with the fore finger and middle finger ioyntly, and therein is the greatest and the strangest conueying shewed. Lastly the same small ball is to be practised in the palme of your hand, and so by vse you shal not only séeme to put any ball from you, and yet retaine it in your hand, but you shall keepe fower or fiue as clenly and certaint as one, this being first learned, and sleight attained vnto, you shal worke wonderful feats, as for example.</p>
               <p>Note for this feaf you must haue foure boxes made in the manner of extinguishers that are made to put out can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, but as big againe: but for want of them you may take smal cādlesticks, or saltseller couers, or som such like.</p>
               <p>Lay three or foure balls before you, and as many boxes or smal candlesticks &amp;c. then first seeme to put one ball
<pb facs="tcp:7497:7"/> into your left hrnd, and therewithall seeme to hold the same fast. Then take one of the boxes &amp;c. or any other thing (hauing a hollow foote, and being great) and seeme to put the Ball which is thought to bee in your left hand vnderneath the same, and so vnder the other candlesticks, Boxes, &amp;c. seeme to bestow the other balls, and all this while the beholders will suppose each ball to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der each box or candlesticks &amp;c. this done vse some charme or forme of wordes (before set downe) hey <hi>Fortuna furie nunquam credo,</hi> passe passe: then take bp the candlestick with one hand and blow, saying thats gone you sée: and so likewise looke vnderneath each candlesticke with like grace and words (sor you must remember to carry a good grace and face on the matter) and the beholders will won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der where they are become: But if you in lifting vp the candlesticke with your right hand leaue all those three or foure balls vnder one of them (as by vse you may easily doe) hauing turned them all downe into your hand and holding them fast with your little, and ring finger) and take the box or candlesticke &amp;c. with your other fingers and cast the balls vp into the hollownesse thereof (for so they wil not rowle so soone away) the standers by wil be much astonished, but it wil séeme wonderful strange, if also in shewing how there remaineth nothing vnder ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the said candlestickes taken vp with your left hand you leaue behind you a great ball, or any other thing, the miracle wil be the greater. For first, they wil thinke you haue pulled away all the Balles by miracle, then that you haue brought them againe by like meanes, and they neither thinke, or looke that any other thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth behinde vnder any of them, and therefore after many other feates done returne to your candlestickes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring where you left the great ball, and in no wise touch the same, but hauing another great ball about you, séeme to bestow the same in manner and forme aforesaid
<pb facs="tcp:7497:7"/> vnder a candlestick which standeth farthest from that where the ball lyeth, and when you shall with words and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>armes séeme to conuey the same ball from vnder the same boxe or candlesticke, &amp;c. (and afterwardes bring it vnder the boxe &amp;c. which you touched not) it wil (I say) séeme wonderfull strange.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To make a little Ball swel in your hand til it be very great.</head>
               <p>TAke a very great ball in your hand, or three indifferent big balls, and shewing one or three little balls, séeme to put them into your said left hand, concealing (as you may wel do) the other balls which were there before: Then vse charmes and wordes and make them seeme to swell, and open your hand &amp;c. This play is to be varied an hundred waies, for as you find them all vnder the boxe or candlestick, so may you go to a stander by and take off his hatte or cappe and shew the balls to be there, by conueying them thereinto as you turne the bottome vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward, These thinges to them that know them are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ridiculous, but to those that are ignorant they are maruelous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To consume or rather conuey one or many Balls into nothing.</head>
               <p>IF you take a ball or more, and seeme to put it into your other hand, and whilst you vse charming wordes, you conuey them out of your right hand into your lapp, it wil séeme strange, for when you open your left hand, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately the sharpest lookers on wil say, it is in your other hand, which also then you may open, and when they sée nothing there they are greatly ouertaken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <pb facs="tcp:7497:8"/>
               <head>Another pretty feat with balls.</head>
               <p>TAke fower Balls, one of the which kéep betwéene your fore-finger and your middle, laying the other thrée vpon the table, then take vp one and put it into your left hand, and afterward take vp another, and conueying it and the other betweene your fingers into your left hand, taking vp the third &amp; séeming to cast it frō you into the ayre or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your mouth, ot else where you please vsing some words or charmes as before: the standers by when you aske them how many you haue in your hand, will iudge there are noe more then two, which when you open your hand they shall sée how they are deluded. But I will leaue to speak of the bal any more; for héerein I might hold you all day, and yet shal I not be able to teach you the vse of it, nor scarsely to vnderstand what I meane or write concerning it, vnlesse you haue had some sight ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of heeretofore by demonstration: and alwayes remember that the right hand be kept open and straight, onely kéepe the palme from view: and therefore I wil end with this miracle,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>A feat, tending chiefely to laughter and mirth</head>
               <p>LAy one ball vpon your shoulder and another on your arme, and the third on the table, which because it is round and wil not easily lye vpon the poynt of your knife, you must bid a stander by, lay it thereon, saying, that you meane to cast all those three balls into your mouth at once: and holding a knife as a penne in your hand, when hee is laying vpon the poynt of your knife, you may easily with the haft rap him on the fingers, for the other mattter wil be hard to doe.</p>
               <p>And thus much of the Balls. To come to the second
<pb facs="tcp:7497:8"/> principall part of Legerdemaine, which is conueyance of mony, wherin by the way obserue that the mony must not be of too small nor to great a circumference, least either, it hinder the conueyance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>Of conueyance of money.</head>
               <p>THe conueying of mony is not much inferiour to the Ball, but much easier to doe: The principall place to keepe a peece of mony in, is the palme of your hand: The best peece to keepe, is a testor, but with excercise all wil be alike, except the money be very small, and then it must be kept betweene the fingers, and almost at the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers end, where as the ball is to be kept, and below neere to the palme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To conuey money out of one hand into the other, by Legerdemaine</head>
               <p>FIrst you must hold open your right hand and lay there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a testor or counter, and then lay there vppon the top of your long left finger, and vse wordes &amp;c. and vpon the sudden slip your right hand from your finger, wherewith you held downe the testor, and bending your hand a very little you shal retaine the testor therein, and sodainely (I say) drawing your right hand through your left, you shall seeme to haue left the testor there, especially when you shut in due time your left hand, which that it may more plainely appeare to be truely done, you may take a knife and seeme to knock against it, so as it shall make a great sound: but in stead of knocking the peece in the left hand (where none is) you shal hold the point of the knife fast with the left hand, and knock against the testor held in the other hand, and it wil bee thought to hit against the mony in the left hand: then vse words, and open the hand,
<pb facs="tcp:7497:9"/> and when nothing is séene it wil be wondred at how the testor was remooued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To conuert or transubstantiate mony into Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or Counters into money.</head>
               <p>AN other way to deceiue the lookers on, is to doe as before with a testor, and kéeping a Counter in the palme of your left hand, secretly to séeme to put the testor thereinto, which being retained stil in the right hand, when the left hand is opened, the testor wil séeme to be transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiated into a counter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To put one Testor into one hand and another into another hand, and with words to bring them together.</head>
               <p>HE that hath once attained to the facillity of retaining one peece of money in his right hand may shew an hundred pleasant conceits by that meanes, &amp; may reserue two or thrée as well as one: and loe, then may you séeme to put one peece into your left hand, and retaining it stil in your right hand you may together therewith take vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother like peece, and so with wordes séeme to bring both péeces together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To put one Testor into a strangers hand, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your owne hand, and to conuay both into the strangers hand with words.</head>
               <p>TAke two testors éeuenly set togeather, and put the same instead of one testor into a strangers hand: And then making as though you put one testor into your left hand, with words you shal make it séeme that you conuey the tstore in your hand into the strangers hand, for when you
<pb facs="tcp:7497:9"/> open your said left hand, there shal be nothing séene: and he opening his hand, shal finde two where he thought was but one. By this deuise I say an hundred conceits may be shewed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To throw a peece of money away and to find it againe where you please.</head>
               <p>YOu may with the the midle and ring-finger of the right hand, conuey a testor into the palme of the same hand, and séeming to cast it away, keepe it still, which with confederacy wil séeme strange: to wit, when you find it againe, where another hath bestowed the very like péece But these things without excercise cannot bee done, and therefore I wil procéede to shew things to bee brought to passe by mony, with lesse difficulty and yet as strange as the rest, which being vnknowne, are maruelously com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, but being knowne, are derided and nothing at all regarded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To make a testor or a groat, leape out of a pot, or run along vppon a table with wordes.</head>
               <p>YOu shall see a Iugler take a testor or groat &amp; throw it into a pot, or lay it on the middle of the table, and with inchanting wordes cause the same to leap out of the pot, or run towards him or from him wardes along the table, which wil séeme miraculous, vntil that you know that it is done with a long black haire of a womans head, fastned to the brim of a groat by meanes of a little hole driuen through with a spanish needle: in like sort you may vse a knife or any other small thing. But if you would haue it to goe from you you must haue a confederate, by which meanes all Iugling is graced, and amended.</p>
               <p>This Feate is the stranger if it bee done by night, a
<pb facs="tcp:7497:10"/> candle placed betweene the lookers on and the Iugler: for by that meanes the eye sight is hindred from discerning the conceit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>A very pretty trick to make a groate or a testor to sinck through a table and to vanish out of a handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe very strangely.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Iugler sometimes wil borrow a groate or a testor, and marke it before you, and séeme to put the same into a handkerchiefe, and wind it so that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter see and féele it: then wil he take you the handkerchiefe and bid you feele whether the groat be there or no: And he wil also require you to put the same vnder a candlestick or some such thing: then wil he send for a bason, and holding the same vnder the boord right against the candlesticke wil vse certaine words of inchauntments, and in short space you shal heare the groat fall into a bason: this done one takes vp the candlesticke, and the Iugler taketh the handkerchiefe by the tassell, and shaketh it: but tho money is gone, which séemeth as strange as any feat whatsoeuer: but being knowne, the miracle is turned into a bable, for it is nothing but to sowe a counter into the corner of a handkerchiefe finely couered with a peece of linnen, little bigger then the counter, which corner you must conuey instéed of the groat deliuered vnto you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the middle of your handkerchiefe, leauing the other ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in your hand or lappe, which afterwards you must séeme to pul through the board, letting it fal into the bason.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To conuey one shilling being in one hand in into an other, holding your armes abroad like to a roode.</head>
               <p>EVermore it is necessary to mingle some merry toyes among your graue miracles as in this case of mony:
<pb facs="tcp:7497:10"/> Take a shilling in each hand, and holding your armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to lay a wager that you wil put them both into one hand without bringing them any whit neerer together: the wager being layd, hold your armes abroad like a rood and turning about with your body lay the shilling out of one of your hands vpon the table, and turning the other side, take it vp with the other hand, and so you shal winne your wager.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>Of Cardes and Dice, with good cautions how to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde cosonage therein: speciall rules to conuey and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the cardes, and the manner and order how to accomplish all difficult and strange iestings wrought with cardes.</head>
               <p>HAuing bestowed some wast money among you I wil set you to Cardes and Dice. A cupple of honest friendes that draw both in a yoake together, which haue beene the ouerthrow of many a hundred in this realme, and these are not the slightest matters wherevppon Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers doe worke, and shew their feates. By which kinde of Iugling a great number haue Iugled away not only their money but also their landes, their health, their time and their honesty: I dare not (as I could shew) the lewd Iugling that cheators practise, least it minister some offence, to the wel disposed, to the simple hurt and losse, and to the wicked occasion of euil doing. But by the way I wil a little speak of Dice, and the vse of them, as caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ats rather to let you beware of their cosonings, then to giue you light to follow their doings: <hi>Non ad imitandum sed euitandum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>First you must know a Langret, which is a die that simple men haue seldome heard of, but often seene to their cost, and this is a wel-fauored die, and seemeth good and square, yet is it forged longer, vppon the Cater, and
<pb facs="tcp:7497:11"/> Trea then any other way: And therefore it is called a Langret. Such be also called bard Cater treas, because commonly the longer end wil of his owne sway drawe downewardes, and turne vp to the eye, Sice, Sincke, Deuce or Ace. The principal vse of them is at <hi>Nouum,</hi> for so long as a paire of Bard cater treas be walking on the bourd, so long can ye not cast fiue nor nine vnles it be by great chance, that the roughnes of the table, or some other stoppe force them to stay, and runne against their kind: for without Cater or trey you know that fiue or nine can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come.</p>
               <p>But you wil say by this reason, he that hath the first dice is like alwayes to strip and rob all the table about. To helpe this, there must be for that purpose, an odde Die, called a flat Catertrea ready at hand, and no other num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for graunting the trea and cater be alwaies vpon the one Die, then is there no chance vppon the other Die, but may serue to make fiue or nine, &amp; cast forth, &amp; loose all.</p>
               <p>But now to show you what shifts they haue to bring the flat die in and out which is a iolly cunning property of Iugling, with them called foysting: the which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but a slight to carry easily within the hand, as often as the foyster list: so that either hee or his partner shal cast the dice, the flat comes not abroad til hee hath made a great hand, and won as much as him listeth: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the flat is euer one, vnles some few times vpon pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he suffer the silly soules to cast in a hand or two, to giue them courage to continue the play and liue in hope of winning.</p>
               <p>These things I know séeme very strange to the simple, and as yet cannot sinke into their braine, how a man may carry so many dice in one hand, and chop and change them so often, and neuer bee espied: so as before I tolde you, Iuglers conueyance séemeth to excéed the compasse of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son till you knowe the feat: but what is it that vse
<pb facs="tcp:7497:11"/> and labour ouercometh not. To foyst finely and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with the same hand to tell mony to and fro, is a thing hardly learned, and asketh a bould spirit and long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, though it be one of the first the Cheater lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
               <p>What should I speake any more of false dice, of fullomes, high-men, low-men, gourds, and brisled dice, grauiers, demies, and contraries, all which haue their sundry vses: but it is not my meaning to stand on this subiect: I would rather vse my pen, and spend my time, to diswade and perswade all gamsters, to beware not not onely with what dice, but with what company and where they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercise gaming: and be well assured Gentlemen that all the friendly entertainment you shall finde amongst them is for no other end, but to perswade you to play, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to breed your great losse, if not altogether your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</p>
               <p>Therefore vtterly forbeare to hazard any thing at dice, and liue in doubt and suspition of cheating, wheresoeuer you play (vnles you know your company very well) for the contagion of cheating is now growne so vniuersall, that they swarme in euery quarter: and therefore yée can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee in safety vnlesse you shunne the company of such altogether.</p>
               <p>To leaue Dice and returne to Cardes, wherein is as much falsehood and cosoning as in Dice: I wil therefore disclose as much in one as in the other, for I would not giue a poynt to choose which of them is the better, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the worse, for there is such a slight in shufling and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the cardes, that play at what game you will, all is lost before hand, but if there bee a confederate either of the players or standers bye, the mischéefe cannot then bee auoyded.</p>
               <p>Beware therefore, when you play among strangers, of him that seemes simple or drunken, for vnder their habit
<pb facs="tcp:7497:12"/> the most speciall Cosoners are presented, and while you thinke by their simplicity and imperfections to beguile them, (and thereof perchance are perswaded by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates (your very friends as you thinke) you your selfe wil be most of all ouertaken.</p>
               <p>Beware also of betters by and lookers on: and namely on them that bet on your side: for whilst they looke on your game without suspition, they discouer it by signes to your aduersaries, with whom they bet, and yet are they confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, whereof me thinkes this one aboue the rest pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth from a fine inuention.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>A tricke by confederacy at Cardes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gamester after he had béene oftentimes bitten with Cheators, and after much losse, grew very suspitious in his play, so that he would not suffer any of the sitters by to be priuy to his game: for this the Cheators deuised a new shift that a woman should sit close by him: and by the swift and slowe drawing of her needle giue notice to the Cheator what was the Cosens game.</p>
               <p>Other helpes there bee, as to set the Cosen vppon the bench, with a looking-glasse behind him on the wal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cheator may alwaies sée what Cardes he hath in his hand, So that a few ensamples in stead of many that might be rehearsed, this one conclusion may be gathered, that whosoeuer is giuen to play, and once sitteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, it is great ods but that hee shal rise a loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser.</p>
               <p>But many there be that liue so continently, that nothing can perswad them to put a penny in aduenture, and some againe are so vnskilful that lack of cunning forceth them to forbeare play: but yet hard it is for any man to fall into their company, but they will make him stoope at one game or other: and for this purpose their first drift and intent is to seeke, by all meanes possible to vnderstand his nature and wherevnto hee is most inclined: if they
<pb facs="tcp:7497:12"/> find that he taketh pleasure in the cōpany of women then séek they to strike him at the sacking law (as they term it) and take this for a rule, that all the Baudes in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try be of the Cheators familiar acquaintance.</p>
               <p>Therefore it is not very hard for them at all times to prouide for their amorous Cosin, alewd letcherous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to kéepe him louing company, then fall they to banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and carousing and hunting of Tauernes, and much is the cost that this silly cosin shal be at in Iewels and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrel, otherwise he shal not once get a graunt to haue a kisse at his mistris lippes: and euer in the middle of their conference, she layeth in this reason, for her sake to put in twenty or thirty Crownes in aduenture at Cardes or Dice: you know not (quoth shée) what may be a womans luck: if he refuse it, Lord how vnkindly shée takes the matter, and cannot be reconciled with lesse then a gowne or a kertle of silke.</p>
               <p>But now if these Cheaters perceiue that hee estéemeth no bruised ware, but is enamored with virginity, they haue a fine cast within an houres warning, to make <hi>Ione Siluerpin</hi> as good a maid as though she had neuer come to the stewes: but to let these thinges passe for offending of chast eares, whose displeasure I would not incurre, for all the cheates these Gamesters get in a whole yeare, but to our purpose.</p>
               <p>There are two sorts of vsing the Cardes, the one is in playing (with one or more) games, as <hi>Primeto, Trumpe, Saunte, Decoye &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other vse of Cardes is to shew feates of Legerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.</p>
               <p>Concerning the first, if it be vsed for recreation, and not to the prophaning of Gods holy name, nor hurt of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and neighbours, they are to be tollerated: but now (more is the pitty) they are not vsed in that fashion as they should be, but much hurt oft times ariseth thereof.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7497:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Primero</hi> now as it is in great vse, so is there much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in it, some play vppon the pricke, some pinch the cards priuily with their nayles, some turne vp the corners, some mark them with fine spots of Ink, some there be that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell into Spaine and into Italy to learne fine tricks and quaint conueyances at cardes, and returne home and win much money with them heare in England, but yet at the last they are stil ouer-reached by some fine wittes that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uise new sleights heere at home.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Trumpe, Saunte,</hi> and such other like games, cutting at the nick is a great aduantage, so is cutting by <hi>Bum-card</hi> finely vnder or ouer: stealing the stock or the discarded Cardes.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Decoye</hi> they drawe twenty handes, together and play all vpon assurance when to winne or loose, other helps there be, as I haue before set downe, with a looking glasse and confederacy: all which and such like, tend to cosening and hurt of our brother: but we wil proceed with the other vse of Cardes, which tendeth to mirth, and recreation of mind, and which in themselues simply is no hurt, vnlesse they are abused. In shewing feats and iugling with cardes the principall poynt consisteth in shufling them nimbly, and alwayes kéeping one certen carde either in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, or in some knowne place of the stock, foure or fiue Cardes from it, héereby you may séeme to worke won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, for it wil be easie for you to see or espie one, which though you be perceiued to doe, it wil not be suspected, if you shufle them wel afterwardes, and this note I must giue you, That in reseruing the bottome Card, you must alwayes (whilst you shuffle) keepe him a little before, or a little behind all the cardes lying vnderneath him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowing him (I say) either a little beyond his fellowes before right ouer the fore finger, or else behind the rest, so as the little finger of the left hand may meete with it, which is the easier and readier, and the better way: In
<pb facs="tcp:7497:13"/> the beginning of your shuffling shuffle as thick as you can, and in the end throw vpon the stock the nether carde (with soe many moe at the least as you would haue preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for any purpose) a little before, or behind the rest; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided alwayes that your fore-finger, if the pack be laide be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, or the little finger if the pack lye behind, creepe vp to méet with the bottome carde, &amp; not lye betwixt the cardes, and when you féele it, you may there hold it vntil you haue shuffled ouer the cardes againe, stil leauing your kept card below, being perfect héerein, you may do almost what you list with the cardes: By this meanes what pack soeuer you make, though it consist of eight, twelue, or twenty cardes you may kéepe them stil together vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uered, next to the nether carde, and yet shuffle them often to satisfie the curious beholders, as for ensample and for breuities sake, to shew you diuers feates vnder one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>How to deliuer out foure Aces, and to conuert them into foure Knaues.</head>
               <p>MAke a pack of eight Cardes, to wit foure knaues and foure Aces, and although all the eight Cardes must lie immediatly together, yet must each Knaue and Ace bée openly seauered, and the same eight cardes must lye also in the lowest place of the bunch, then shuffle them soe, as alwayes at the second shuffling, or at least wise at the end of your shuffling the said pack, and of the pack one ace may lye nethermost, or so as you may know where hee go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and lyeth, and alwaies I say let your foresaid pack, with thrée or foure cardes more, lie vnseperably together immediately vppon and with that ace, then vsing some speech or other deuise, and putting your hand with the cardes to the edge of the table, to hide the account, let out priuily a péece of the second card, which is one of the knaues holding forth the stock in both your handes, and
<pb facs="tcp:7497:14"/> shewing to the standers by the nether Card, (which is the ace or kept Card) couering also the head or péece of the knaue (which is your next Card) with your foure fingers: draw out the same knaue laying it downe on the table: thē shuffle againe, kéeping your pack whole, &amp; so haue you two aces lying together in the bottome, &amp; therfore to reforme that disordered Card, as also for a grace and countenance to that action, take off the vppermost Card of the bunch, &amp; thrust it into the middest of the Cardes, and then take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the nethermost Card which is one of your aces, and bestow him likewise: then may you begin as before, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an other ace, and in stead thereof lay downe another knaue, and so forth, vntil in stead of your foure aces you haue laid downe foure knaues. The beholders all this while thinking that there lye foure aces on the table, are greatly abused and wil maruaile at the transformation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>How to tell one what Card hee seeth in the bottome, when the same Card is shuffled into the stocke.</head>
               <p>VVHen you haue séene a Card priuily, or as though you marked it not, lay the same vndermost, and shuffle the Cardes as before you were taught, till your Card lye againe below in the bottome: then shew the same to the be holders, willing them to remember it, then shuffle the Cardes or let any shuffle them, for you know the Cardes already, and therefore may at any time tel them what Card they saw, which neuerthelesse would be done with great circumstance, and lesse shew of difficulty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>A strange and excellent trick to hold foure Kings in the hand, and by words to transforme them into foure Aces, and after to make them all blank Cards, one after another.</head>
               <p>YOu shall sée a Iugler take foure Kinges and no more in his hand, and apparantly shew you them, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter some wordes and charmes, he wil throw them downe before you vppon the table, taking one of the Kings away
<pb facs="tcp:7497:14"/> and adding but one other Card: then taking them vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and blowing vpon them, wil shew you them trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into blanck Cardes, white on both sides: after v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing charmes againe, throwing them downe as before, (with the faces downeward) wil take them vp againe and shew you foure Aces, blowing stil vpon them, that it may bréed the more wonder, which trick in my mind is nothing inferiour to the rest: and being not knowne wil séeme won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull strange to the spectators, yet after you know it you cannot choose but say the trick is pretty. Now therefore to accomplish this feat you must haue Cardes made for the purpose, (halfe Cardes you may call them) that is the one halfe kings, the other part aces, so that laying the aces one ouer the other, nothing but the kings wil be seene, and then turning the Kinges downeward, the foure aces wil be seene, prouided you must haue two whole, one whole king to couer one of the aces, or els it wil be perceiued, and the other an ace to lay ouer the Kings, when you meane to shew the aces: then when you wil make them all blanke, lay the Cards a little lower, and hide the aces and they wil appeare all white. The like you may make of the foure knaues, putting vppon them the foure fiues, and so of the rest of the Cardes: But this cannot bee wel shewed you without demonstration.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I haue intreated of the three principal kinds of Iugling, now it remaineth in order to speak of Iugling by confederacy, which is either priuate or publike.</p>
               <p>Priuate confederacy is, when one (by a special plot laid by himselfe, without any compact made with others) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swadeth the beholders, that he wil suddenly and in their presence, do some miraculous feate, which he hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy accomplished priuately: as for ensample, hee wil shew you a Card or any other like thing, and wil say further vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, behold and see what a mark it hath, and then bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it, and neuertheles fetcheth another Carde, soe
<pb facs="tcp:7497:15"/> marked out of some bodies pocket, or out of some corner, where he himselfe before had placed it, to the wonder and astonishment of simple beholders, which conceaue not that kinde of illusion, but expect miracles and strange workes.</p>
               <p>I haue read of a notable exploit done before a king by a Iugler, who painted on a wall the picture of a done, and séeing a pidgion sitting vppon the top of an house said to the King, loe now your grace shal sée what a Iugler can doe if he be his craftes master, &amp; then pricked the picture with a knife, so hard &amp; so often, &amp; with soe effectual words as the pidgion fel downe from the top of the house starke dead, you may imagine how the matter was taken, what wondring was thereat, how he was prohibited to vse that feat any further, least hee should imploy it in any other kind of murder, This story is held yet of diuers as cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, but when you are taught the feat or slight, you wil thinke it a mockery and a simple illusion.</p>
               <p>To vnfold you the mistery héereof, so it is that the poore pigeon was before in the hands of the Iugler, into whom he had thrust a dramme of <hi>Nux vomica,</hi> or some other such poyson, which to the nature of the Bird was so extreame a poyson, as after the receipt thereof it could not liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the space of halfe an houre, and being let loose after the medicine ministred, she alwayes resorteth to the top of the next house, which she wil the rather doe, if ther be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pigeons already sitting there, and after a short space falleth downe, either starke dead, or greatly astonished: but in the meane time, the Iugler vseth wordes of art, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to protract time, and partly to gaine credit, and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the beholders.</p>
               <p>As with Cardes you may shew feates by priuate confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, so of the other two, that is to wit, with the balls and the mony, as to marke a shilling or any other thing, and throw the same into a riuer or déepe pond, and hauing
<pb facs="tcp:7497:15"/> hid the shilling before, with like markes in some other se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place, bid some go presently and fetch it, making them beleeue that it is the very same you threw into the riuer, the beholders will maruaile much at it: and of such feats there may be many done, but more by publik confederacy, whereby one may tel another how much money hee hath in his purse, and an hundred like toyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>Of publicke confederacy, and whereof it consisteth.</head>
               <p>PVblike confederacy is, when there is before hand a compact made betwixt diuers persons: the one to bee principal, the other to be assistant in working of miracles or rather in cosoning and abusing the beholders, as when I tel you in the presence of a multitude, what you haue thought or done, or shall do or thinke, when you and I were therevppon agréed before: and if this bee cunningly and closely handled, it wil induce great admiration to the beholders, especially when they are before amased and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused, by some experiment of art Magick or Legerde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine. I wil in briefe set downe some pretty conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and soe I will procéed with other feates in other kindes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To tel you how to know whether you cast Crosse or Pile by the ringing.</head>
               <p>LAy a wager with your Confederate (who must séeme simple or obstinate opposed against you) that standing behind a doore you wil (by the sounding or ringing of the money) tel him whether he cast crosse or pile, soe as when you are gone, and hee hath phillipped the mony before the witnesses who are to be cosoned, hee must say, <hi>What is it</hi> if it bee crosse, or <hi>What i'st</hi> if it be pile, or some such signe as you are agréed vppon, and soe you néede not faile to gesse rightly. By this meanes if you haue any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, you may seeme to doe an hundred miracles, and to discouer a mans thought or words spoken a far off.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <pb facs="tcp:7497:16"/>
               <head>How to tel where a stolne horse is become.</head>
               <p>BY meanes of confederacy <hi>Cuthbert conicatcher,</hi> and one <hi>Swart Rutter,</hi> two that haue taken degrees in <hi>Whittington Colledge,</hi> abused notably the countrey peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for <hi>Cuthbert</hi> would hide away his neighbours horses, kine, colts, &amp;c. and send them to <hi>Swart Rutter,</hi> (whom he before had told where they were) promising to send the parties vnto him, whom he described and made knowne by diuers signes: so as this <hi>Swart</hi> would tel them at their first entrance vnto the doore wherefore they came, and would say that their horses, kine &amp;c. were stolne, but the theefe should be forced to bring them back againe within one mile (south and by west &amp;c.) of his house: euen as the plot was layd and the pack made before by <hi>Cuthbert</hi> and him. This <hi>Cuthbert</hi> is esteemed of some and thought to be a witch of others, he is accounted a coniurer, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called a wise man, and are able of themselues, to tell you where any thing that is stolne is, as to build <hi>Pauls</hi> steeple vp againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To make one dance naked.</head>
               <p>IT hath beene reported of such fellowes, and such, that can do rare feates, as to make one dance naked. To the effecting of this, make a poore boy confederat with you, so as after charmes and wordes spoken by you, he vncloth himselfe and stand naked: seeming (whilst he vndresseth him) to shake, stampe, and cry, stil hastening to bee vncloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, til he be stark naked: or if you can procure none to go so farre, let him onely begin to stamp and shake, &amp;c. and to vncloth him, and then you may (for reuerence of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany) seeme to release him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To make a pot for any such thing standing fast on a cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bord, to fall downe thence by vertue of words.</head>
               <p>LEt your cupbord be so placed, as your confederate may hould a black Threed without in the courte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde
<pb facs="tcp:7497:16"/> some window of that roome, and at a certaine lowd word spoken by you, he may pull the same threed, being wound about the pot. And this was the feate of <hi>Eleazer</hi> the <hi>Iewe,</hi> which <hi>Iosephus</hi> reporteth to be such a miracle.</p>
               <p>Now that wee haue spoken of the three principall actes of Legerdemaine and of confederacie, I will goe forward, and touch some fewe ordinary feates which are pretty, yet not altogether to be compared with the rest; I meane for conceipt and nimblenes of the hand, yet such as to the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and those that know not the carriage, will seeme strange and wonderfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>Of Boxes to alter one graine into another, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume the corne or graine to nothing.</head>
               <p>THere be diuers iugling boxes with false bottomes, wherein many false feates are wrought. First they haue a boxe couered or rather footed alike at each end, the bottome of the one end being no deeper then as it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine one lane of corne or pepper, glewed therevpon: Then vse they to put into the hollow end therof some other kinde of graine, ground or vnground: then do they couer it, and put it vnder a hat or candlesticke, and either in putting it therinto, or pulling it thence, they turne the boxe, and open the contrary end, wherein is shewed a contrary graine, or else they shew the glewed end first, (which end they sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly thrust into a bag of such graine as is glewed already therevpon) and secondly the empty boxe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>How to conuey (with words and charmes) the corne conteined in one Boxe, into another.</head>
               <p>THere is another boxe fashioned like a bell, whereinto they put so much and such corne as the foresaid hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe boxe can conteine: then they stop and couer the same with a peece of lether as broad as a tester, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thrust vp hard to the middle part or waste of the said bell, will sticke fast and beare vp the corne, and if the edge of the same lether be wet, it will hold the better: then take
<pb facs="tcp:7497:17"/> they the other boxe, dipped (as is aforesaid) in corne, and set downe the same vpon the Table, the empty end vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, saying, that they wil conuey the graine therein, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other boxe or bell, which beeing set downe some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hard vpon the table, the leather and corne therein wil fall downe, so as the said bell being taken vp from the table, you shall see Corne lying thereon, &amp; the stopple wil be hidden therewith, and couered: and when you vncouer the other boxe nothing shal remaine therein, but presently the corne must bee swept downe with one hand, into the other, or into your lappe or hat: many feates may be done with this boxe, as to put therein a toade, affirming the same to be so turned from corne, and then many beholders wil suppose the same to be the Iuglers diuel, whereby his feates and miracles are wrought.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>How to pull Laces innumerable out of your mouth of what colour or length you list, and neuer any thing seene to be therein.</head>
               <p>AS for pulling of laces forth of the mouth it is now somewhat stale, where by Iuglers get much money among maydes, selling lace by the yard, putting into their mouthes one round bottome as fast as they pull out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and at the iust end of euery yard they tie a knott, soe as the same resteth vppon their téeth, then cut they off the same, and so the beholders are double and treble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, éeing so much lace as will be contained in a hat, and the same of what colour you list to name, to be drawne by so euen yardes out of his mouth, and yet the Iugler to talke as though there were nothing at all in his mouth.</p>
               <p>There are diuers Iugling tricks, which I am loth to describe for some reasons before alleaged, whereof some are common, some rarer, and some desperate: I wil therefore shew a few desperate and dangerous iugling
<pb facs="tcp:7497:17"/> knackes, wherein the simple are made to think that a silly Iugler with words can hurt and help, kill and reuiue any creature at his pleasure: and first to kill any kind of pullen and make them reuiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To kill a Hen, Chicken, or Capon, and giue it life againe.</head>
               <p>TAke a hen &amp;c. and thrust an aule, or a fine sharp poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted knife through the midst of the head thereof, the edge towards the bill,<note place="margin">The naturall cause why a Hen thrust through the head with a Bodkin doth live notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</note> so as it may séeme impossible for her to escape death, Then vse wordes or incantations, and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out the knife, lay otes before her, and she wil eate and liue, being nothing at all greeued or hurt with the wound, because the braine lyeth soe far behind in the head as it is not touched though you thrust your knife betwéene the combe and it: And after you haue done this you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert your spéech and actions, to the gréeuous wounding &amp; recouering of your owne selfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To eat a knife, and to fetch it forth of another place.</head>
               <p>TAke a knife, and conuey the same betwéene your two hands, so as no parte be séene thereof, but a little of the poynt, which you must so bite at the first as noyse may be made therewith: then séeme to put a great part thereof into your mouth, and letting your hand slippe downe, there wil appeare to haue bin more in your mouth, then is possible to be contained therein: then send for drinke, or vse some other delay vntil you haue let the said knife slippe into your lappe, holding both your fists close together as before, and then rais them so from the edge of the table where you sit (for from thence the knife may most priuily slip downe into your lappe) and in stead of biting the knife knab a little vppon your naile, and then séeme to thrust the knife into your mouth, opening the hand next vnto it, and thrust vp the other, so as it may appeare to the stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb facs="tcp:7497:18"/> by, that you haue deliuered your hands thereof, and thrust it into your mouth: then cal for drinke, after coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance made of pricking, and daunger &amp;c. lastly put your hand into your lap, and taking that knife into your hand you may seeme to bring it out from behind you, or from whence you list: but if you haue another like knife, and a confederate, you may do twenty notable wonders hereby: as to send a stranger by into some garden, or Orchard, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing to him some tree or hearb vnder which it sticketh or else some strangers sheath or pocket &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To thrust a bodkin through your head without any hurt.</head>
               <p>TAke a bodkin so made, as the haft being hollow, the blade there of may slip thereinto: as soone as you hold the poynt vpward, and set the same to your forehead: and séeme to thrust it into your head: and so (with a little spunge in your hand) you may wring out blood or wine, making the beholders think the blood or wine (whereof you may say you haue drunke very much) runneth out of your forehead: Then after countenance of paine &amp; greefe, pul away your hand suddenly, holding the poynt downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and it wil fall so out, as it wil seeme neuer to haue bin thrusted into the hafte: But immediately thrust that bodkin into your lappe or pocket, and pul out another plaine bodkin like the same, sauing in that conceit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To cut halfe your nose in sunder and to heale it againe presently without any salue.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This is easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit beeing nimbly done it will deceiue the fight of the beholders.</note>TAe a knife hauing a round hollow gappe in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and lay it vpon your nose, and so shal you seeme to haue cut your nose in sunder: prouided alwayes that in all these, you haue another like knife withou a gap to be shewed vppon pulling out of the same, and wordes
<pb facs="tcp:7497:18"/> of inchantments to speake: Blood also to Bewray the wound, and nimble conueyance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>To put a Ring through your cheeke.</head>
               <p>THere is a pretty knack, which séemeth dangerous to the chéeke: for the accomplishment whereof, you must haue two rings of like coulour and quantity, the one filed asunder, so as you may thrust it vpon your cheeke: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther must be whole and conueyed vppon a sticke, holding your hand therevppon in the middle of the sticke, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring each end of the same sticke to be holden fast by a stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by, then pulling the ring out of your cheeke, cleanely strike it against some part of the sticke, keeping it stil in your hand, then pull your other hand from the sticke, and pulling it away, whirle about the ring and so it wil be thought that you haue put thereon the ring that was in your chéeke.</p>
               <p>Many other pretty feates of this nature might be heere set downe, as to cut off ones head and to lay it in a platter, which Iuglers call the decollation of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> also to thrust a dagger or bodkin through your guttes, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry strangely, and to recouer immediately, after another way then with the bodkin before rehearsed: also to draw a cord through your nose, mouth or hand so sencibly, as is wonderfull to see, all which with many more I here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare for breuities sake. There is a very pretty trick to make wine or beere to come out of your brow or eare with a funnell after you haue drunke the same, the which I am loth to discouer, as not willing to haue all the poore Iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers trickes made knowne at once: there is a way to make fire to come out of your mouth by burning of towe, all which, for reasons before aleadged, I wil heere omit to discouer, But wil hie me to another sort of Iuglers, or rather cosoners, calling themselues by the name of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimists, professing themselues learned men, and to haue the Philosophers stone: these professors of the misty or
<pb facs="tcp:7497:19"/> smoakie science, studie and cast about how to ouer-reach and cosin the simple, and such as are giuen to couetousnes or greedy desire after gaine, with such they insinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues by little and little, professing a shew of honesty and plainenes, vntil they are acquainted with their desires, and found the length of their foote: telling them that they can do wonders, make siluer of copper, and golde of siluer. Such a one a while a goe was in Battersey, who comming poore to towne, made some of the towne beléeue he had the philosophers stone: wherevppon one of the rest beleeuing him, desired to bée better acquainted with him: insomuch that he requested him to take a poore bedde at his house, and offered him great kindnesse, hoping in time to get some skil of him towards the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Philosophers stone: vppon a day as this Smith (for so imagine him to be) and beggerly Artist were together, desired him of all loues to impart to him some of his learning, assuring him, if it lay in his power to doe him a pleasure he would not faile, protesting that both his purse and himselfe were both at his command: Herevpon to be short, my Gentleman at the first was somwhat scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous, yet at the earnest request of his new friend did at last condiscend, charging him to be secret in what he should disclose vnto him. The Smith swore to bee silent: then my cosoning copesmate instructs him as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>In the month of Iuly, search for the séede of Fearne, which must bee first and principall matter of working this, and effecting this hidden secret, and quoth he if you had but an ounce of this fearneseed, thou shalt be made for euer, for it is very hard to find: heerevppon he gets vp the next morning (for it was about the same time of the yeare which hee prescribed him to search for this inestimable seed) and lookes very diligently about the heath, where store of fearne growes: but hauing spent most part
<pb facs="tcp:7497:19"/> of the day in searching and looking, his backe ready to cracke with stooping, and his throate furd with dust, for want of small béere, so that the poore Smith was ready to faint for want of foode: by chance one of the towne came by, and séeing him search so diligently vp and downe, and could not guesse for what, asked him what he sought for so busily? O quoth the Smith, for a thing that if I could find, I should be made for euer: why quoth the fellow what I prethée ist? O no quoth the Smith I may not tell you: not tell me quoth the fellow, why what ist? I prethee tell me: at last, at the earnest entreaty of the fellow, the Smith told he looked for fearne séede: with that the fellow laughed a good, and asked him who willed him to looke for that? that did M. <hi>Etseb</hi> quoth the Smith, and if I can but finde one ounce of it, it would bee of much worth: worth quoth the fellow, he that set thée to look for that was a foole and thou art an Asse, for there was neuer any fearne seed as yet son: therefore get thee home to thy forge, for hee makes but a foole of thée: at this the Smith was blancke, and got him home to his anuil: but how the Smith and the Alcumister, agréed vpon the reckoning for his cosening him, I meane not héere to deliuer: but this I bring in by the way, to shew that their art is nothing but deceipt, and themselues coso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which by two pretty tales I will declare vnto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>How an Alcumister cousoned a Priest.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHaucer</hi> in one of his Canterbury tales, rehearseth this iest of a cousoning Alcumist: espying on a day a couetous priest, whose purse hee knew to bee well lined: assaulted him with flatterie and kinde speech, two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall points belonging to this art: at length hee borrowed money of this priest, which is the third part of this art, without the which the professors can doe no good, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in good estate: then he at his day repayed the mony, which is the most difficult point in this art, and a rare
<pb facs="tcp:7497:20"/> experiment: finally to rquite the priests curtesie, he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto him such instructions, as therby within short time he should become infinitely rich, and all through this art of multiplication: and this is the most common point in this science, for herein they must be skilfull before they bee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous or attaine to any credit: the Priest disliked not his proffer, especially because it tended to his profit, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced his curtesie: then the foole-taker bad him send forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with for three ounces of quicke-siluer, which he said he would transubstantiate (by his art) into perfect siluer: the Priest thought nothing of deceit, but with great ioy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished his request.</p>
               <p>And now forsooth goeth this iolly Alcumist about his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sines, and worke of multiplication, and causeth the Priest to make a fire of coles, in the bottome whereof he placeth a croslet, and pretending onely to help the Priest to lay the coles handsomely, he foysteth into the middle ward or lane of coles, a béechen cole, within which was conueyed an ingot of perfect siluer, which when the cole was consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med slipt downe into the croslet, that was I say directly vnder it. The Priest perceiued not the fraud, but receiued the ingot of siluer, and was not a little ioyfull to see such certain successe procéed from his own handy worke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in could be no fraud (as he surely conceiued) and therefore very diligently gaue the knaue forty pounds, for the receit of this experiment, who for that summe of money, taught him a lesson in Alcumistry, but he neuer returned to heare repetitions, or to see how he profited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <head>A merry tale how a cousoning Alcumist deceiued a country Gentleman.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Gentleman in Kent of good worth, not long sithence was ouertaken by a cousoning knaue, who professed Alcumistry, Iugling, Witch-craft, and coniuration, and by meanes of his companions and confederates, found
<pb facs="tcp:7497:20"/> the simplicitie &amp; abilitie of the said Gentleman, and learnt his estate and humors to bee conuenient for his purpose, and at last came a wooing to his daughter, to whom he made loue cunningly in words, though his purpose ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to another end: and among other illusions and tales, concerning his owne commendations, for wealth, paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, inheritance, alliance, learning and cunning, he bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted of the knowledge and experience in Alcumistry, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the simple Gentlema a beleeue that he could multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and of one Angell make two or three, which seemed strange to the Gentleman: insomuch as he became wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling enough to see that conclusion: whereby the Alcumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster had more hope and comfort to attaine his desire, then if his daughter had yeelded to haue married him: to be short, he in the presence of the said Gentleman, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude within a little ball of virgins waxe a couple of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and after certaine ceremonies and coniuring words, hee seemed to deliuer the same vnto him, but in truth, through Legerdemaine, he conueied into the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hand, another ball of the same scantling, wherein were inclosed many more Angels then were in the ball which hee thought he had receiued. Now (forsooth) the Alcumister bad him lay vp the same ball of waxe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so vse certaine ceremonies, (which I thought good heere to omit) and after certaine daies, houres, and minutes, they returned together according to the appointment, and found great gaines by multiplication of the angels, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he being a plaine man, was hereby perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he should not onely haue a rare and notable good sonne in law, but a companion that might help to adde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wealth much treasure, and to his estate great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and felicitie: and to increase this opinion in him, as also to win his further fauour, but especially to bring his cunning Alcumistry, or rather his leud purpose to passe, he told him that it were folly to multiply a pound of gold,
<pb facs="tcp:7497:21"/> when as easily they might multiply a million, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore counselled him to produce all the mony he had, or could borrow of his neighbours, and friends, and did put him out of doubt, that he would multiply the same, and redeuble it excéedingly, euen as he saw by experience how he dealt with the small summe before his face: this Gent. in hope of gaines and preferment, consented to his swéet motion, and brought out and laid before his feet, not the one halfe of his goods, but all that he had, or could make or borrow any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way: then this Iuggling Alchimister hauing obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his purpose, foulded the same in a bail in quantity far bigger then the other. And conuaying the same vnto his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some or pocket, deliuered another Ball (as before) in the like quantitie, to be reserued, and safely kept in his chest, whereof (because the matter was of importance) either of them must haue a key, and a seuerall locke, that no inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption might be made to the ceremonie, or abuse by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them in defrauding each other. Now forsooth the circumstances, and ceremonies being ended, and the Alchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misters purpose thereby performed, he told the Gent. that vntill a certaine day and houre limited to returne, either of them might imploy themselues about their busines, and necessarie affaires, the Gent. to his businesse, and hee to the Citie of London. And in the meane time the golde should multiply. But the Alchimister (belike hauing other matters of more importance) came not iust at the hower appointed nor yet at the day, nor within the yeere, so as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were somewhat against the Gent. conscience to violate his promise or breake the league, yet partly by the longing he had to see, and partly the desire hee had to enioy the fruit of the excellent experiment, hauing for his owne security (and the others satisfaction) some testimony at the opening thereof, to witnes his sincere dealing, he brake vp the coffer, and loe, he soone espied the Ball of waxe which he himselfe had laid vp there with his owne hands, so as
<pb facs="tcp:7497:21"/> hee thought, if the hardest should fall, he should finde his principall, and why not as good increase now, as of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before? But alas, when the waxe was broken and the mettall discouered, the gold was much abased and became perfect lead.</p>
               <p>Hitherto haue I spoken somewhat of the knauerie of Alcumistry, now I will conclude with a pretty dialogue that <hi>Petrarke</hi> a man of great wisedome and learning, and of no lesse experience, hath written: who as in his time, saw the fraudulent fetches of this compassing craft, so hath there been no age, since the same hath been broached, but that some wise men haue smelt out the euill meaning of these shifting marchants, and bewrayed them to the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Petrarke,</hi> (I say) treating of the same matter, in forme of a dialogue, introduceth a disciple of his, who fancied the foresaid profession and practise, speaking on this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Discip.</hi> I hope for a prosperous successe in Alcumistry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> It is a wonder from whence that hope should spring, sith the fruit thereof did neuer yet fall to thy lot: nor yet at any time chance to another, as the report commonly goeth, that many rich men, by this vanity and madnes, haue been brought to beggery, whilst they haue wearied themselues therewith, weakned their bodies, and wasted their wealth, in trying of conclusions: to make gold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender gold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Discip.</hi> I hope for gold according to the workemans promise.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> He that promised the gold, will runne away with thy gold, and thou neuer the wiser.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Discip.</hi> He promiseth me great good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petr.</hi> He will first serue his owne turne, and releeue his priuate pouerty, for Alcumisters are a beggerly kind of people, who though they confesse themselues bare, and
<pb facs="tcp:7497:22"/> needy: yet will they make other rich, and wealthy, as though others pouertie did molest, and greeue them more then their owne, so farre the words of <hi>Petrarke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albert</hi> in his booke of mineralls, reporteth that <hi>Auicen</hi> treating of Alcumistry: saith, Let the dealers of Alcumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry vnderstand, that the very nature of things, can not be changed: but rather made by Arte, to resemble the same in shew, and likenes: so that they are not tho very thing indéede but séeme to be in appearance: As Castles and Towers doe seeme to be built in the ayre, whereas the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentations there are shewed, are nothing else, but the resemblance of certaine obiects belowe, caused in some bright, and cleere cloud, when the aire is voide of thicknes, and grosenes, a sufficient proofe hereof may be the looking glasse: and we sée (saith hee) the yellow orrenge coulour laid vpon red, seemeth to be gold.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the fond, and vaine arte of Alcumistry, I will now draw to an ende, leauing to speake of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable charmes of coniurours, bad Phisitions, lewd Surgeons, melancholy Witches, and cosoners, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for such as bad Phisitions and Surgeons, know not how to cure: as against the falling euill, the biting of mad dogs, the stinging of a Scorpion, the tooth-ach, for a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in trauell, for the kings euill: to get a thorne out of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny member, or a bone out of ones throate: for sore eies, to open locks, against spirits: for the botts in a horse, for sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er wines, and diuers others.</p>
               <p>There are also diuers bookes imprinted, as it should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the authoritie of the Church of Rome, wherin are contained many medicinall prayers, not onely against all diseases of horses, but also for euery impediment, and fault in a horse, in so much as if a shooe fall in the middest of his iourney; there is a prayer to warrant your horses hoofe so as it shall not breake, how far soeuer he be from the Smithes forge: but these of all the rest are the fondest
<pb facs="tcp:7497:22"/> toyes, that euer were deuised, therefore we will passe them ouer, and yet how many in these daies are addicted to the beléefe of these charmes it is incredible, I will giue you a taste of two or three, because you shall see the foolery of the rest.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charm">
               <head>A Charme to be said each morning by a Witch fasting, or at least before she goe abroad.</head>
               <p>THe fire bites, the fire bites, the fire bites: hogs turde ouer it, hogs turde ouer it, hogs turd ouer it. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with thee, the Sonne with me, the holy Ghost be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéen vs both to be, thrise, then spit ouer one shoulder, and then ouer the other, and then three times right forward.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charm">
               <head>An olde womans Charme wherewith she did much good in the country and grew famous thereby.</head>
               <p>AN old woman that healed all diseases of cattell (for the which she neuer tooke any reward but a penny and a loafe) being seriously examined, by what words she brought these things to passe, confessed that after shee had touched the sicke creature, shee alwaies departed immediately saying.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>My loafe in my lap,</l>
                  <l>My penny in my purse:</l>
                  <l>Thou art neuer the better,</l>
                  <l>And I am neuer the worse.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="charm">
               <head>A slouenly Charme for eies.</head>
               <q>
                  <l>The Diuell pull out thine eies,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>etish</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Spel this word backward and you shall see what aslouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charme this is <hi>etish.</hi>
                     </note>in the holes likewise.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="charm">
               <p>
                  <hi>A</hi> Miller that had his eeles stolne by night, made mone to the priest of the parish, who indeede was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of the theeues that stole the eeles, Sir Iohn willed him to be quiet, for said he I will so curse the theeues, and their adherents with bell, booke, and candle, that they
<pb facs="tcp:7497:23"/> shall haue small ioy of their fish, and therefore the next Sonday Sir Iohn got him vp to the pulpit with his sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis on his back, and his Gole about his necke, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced these words following, in the audience of the people.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>All ye that haue stolne the Millers Eeles</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laudate Dominum in coelis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And all they that haue consented therevnto,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Benedicamus Domino.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>By this little you may plainely perceiue the fopperie of the Church of Rome, who hold such toyes as authenticall, and also their knauerie, to make the people beleeue lies for truth, and falshood for honestie, Bearing them in hand, as in this, so in all the rest, with blindnes, and ignorance: but hereof inough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="trick">
               <p>And now to conclude, let vs backe againe with one pretty knack, which is held to be marueilous and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And that is to make a horse tell you how much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney you haue in your purse: and I reade of a pretty storie of an asse at <hi>Memphis</hi> in Egypt, that could doe rare feates, among other Iuggling knackes, there and then vsed: there was one that tooke paines with an asse, that hee had taught him all these qualities following, and for game hee caused a stage to bee made, and an assembly of people to meete, which being done in the manner of a play, he came in with his asse, and said: The <hi>Sultan</hi> hath great neede of asses, to helpe to carrie stones, and other stuffe towards his great building which hee hath in hand: the asse immediately fell down to the ground, and by all signes shewed himselfe to bee sicke, and at length to giue vp the ghost, so as the Iuggler begged of the assembly money towards his asse, and hauing gotten all that hee could, he said, now my masters you shall sée mine asse is yet aliue, and doth but counterfet, because hee would haue some
<pb facs="tcp:7497:23"/> money to buy him prouender, knowing that I was poore and in some néed of reliefe: herevpon he would needs lay a wager that his asse was aliue, who to euery mans seeing was starke dead: and when one had laid money with him therevpon, he commanded the asse to arise, but he lay still as though he were dead: then did he beat him with a cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, but that would not serue the turne, vntill he had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressed his spéech to the Asse, saying as before in open au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, the <hi>Sultane</hi> hath commanded that all the people shall ride out to morrow, and see the triumph, and that the faire Ladies will ride vpon the fairest Asses, and will giue notable prouender to them, and euery Asse shall drinke of the swéet water of Nylus: And then, loe the Asse did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently start vp, and aduance himselfe exceedingly. Loe quoth his master, now I haue wonne: but in troth the Maior hath borrowed my Asse for the vse of the old il-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured witch his wife: and therevpon immediatly he hung downe his eares and halted downe right, as though he had beene starke lame: then said his Master, I perceiue you loue yong pretty wenches: at which the asse looked vp as it were with a ioifull chéere; and then his master bade him choose out one that should ride vpon him, and he ran to a very hansome woman, and touched her with his head.</p>
               <p>Such a one is at this day to be seene in London, his master will say, sirra, héere be diuers Gentlemen, that haue lost diuers things, and they heare say that thou canst tell them tidings of them where they are: if thou canst, prethée shew thy cunning and tell them: then hurles hee downe a handkercher or a gloue that he had taken from the parties before, and bids him giue it the right owner, which the horse presently doth: and many other pretty feates this horse doth, and some of those trickes as the Asse before mentioned did, which not one among a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand perceiues how they are done, nor how he is brought to learne the same: and note that all the feates that this
<pb facs="tcp:7497:24"/> horse doth, is altogether in numbering: as for ensample, his maister will aske him how many people there are in the roome? the horse will pawe with his foot so many times as there are people: and marke the eye of the horse is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies vpon his master, and as his master moues, so goes he or stands still, as he is brought to it at the first: as for ensample, his master will throw out three dice, and will bid his horse tell how many you or he haue throwne, then the horse pawes with his foote whiles the master stands stone still: then when his master sées he hath pawed so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as the first dice shewes it selfe, then he lifts vp his shol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and stirres a little: then hee bids him tell what is on the second die, and then of the third die, which the horse will doe accordingly, still pawing with his foote vntill his master sées he hath pawed inough, and then stirres: which the horse marking, will stay and leaue pawing. And note, that the horse will pawe an hundred times together, vntill he sees his master stirre: and note also that nothing can be done, but his master must first know, and then his master knowing, the horse is ruled by him by signes. This if you marke at any time you shall plainely perceiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>NOw that we are come to our iourneies end, let vs sit downe and looke about vs, whether we are all sonnes of one father, if there be no knaues among vs: St. <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> light me the candle. Who doe I sée? what the lusty lad of the Myter, that will binde beares, and ride his golden Asse to death but he will haue his will? Birlady, birlady sir, you of all the rest are most welcome, what? how doth your stomack after your carrowsing banquet? what gorgs vpon gorge, egges vpon egges, and sack vpon sack, at these yeares? by the faith of my body sir you must prouide for a hot kitchen against one grow olde, if you meane to liue my yeares: but happy the father that begot thee, and thrife happy the Nurse that fostred such a toward yonker as thy
<pb facs="tcp:7497:24"/> selfe: I know thy vertues aswell as thy selfe, thou hast a superficiall twang of a little something: an Italian ribald cannot vomit out the infections of the world, but thou my pretty Iuuenall, an English Horrell-lorrell, must lick it vp for restoratiue, and putrifie thy gentle brother ouer against thée, with the vilde impostumes of thy lewd corruptions: God blesse good mindes from the blacke enemy say I: I know you haue beene prying like the Diuell from East to West, to heare what newes: I will acquaint thee with some, and that a secret distillation before thou goest. Hee that drinketh oylc of prickes, shall haue much a doe to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid sirrop of roses: and he that eateth nettles for prouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, hath a priuiledge to piffe vpon lillies for litter. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thée swéet natures darling, insult not ouermuch vpon quiet men: a worme that is troden vpon will turne againe, and patience loues not to be made a cart of Croyden. I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with thee now, but if I sée thee not mend thy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Ile tell thée another tale shortly: thou shalt sée that I can doot: I could bring in my Author to tell thée to thy face, that he hath found a knaue in grosse, of thée: but I can say, I haue found thée a foole in retaile: thou séest simplicitie can not double, nor plaine dealing cannot dissemble, I could wish thee to amend thy life, and take heed of the Beadle.</p>
               <q>Vale qui rediculose haec legeris.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>